Guide to the Filippo Tommaso Marinetti Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings by Filippo Tommaso Marinetti, 1895-1944; Series IV; 11.5; (28 boxes)
  - WRITINGS
    - La maison magique de Depero
      - Autograph manuscript essay, with a few corrections, signed at bottom of last page. Several pages have sections from a printed essay cut out, pasted, and integrated into this essay. The excerpts constitute most of the first four paragraphs of the manifesto La splendeur geometrique et mecanique et la sensi- bilite numerique (1914 Mar 11). Possibly written in 1921 as first sentence reads: "Nous autres futu- ristes, nous avons commencé, il y a douze ans..." 8 p., numbered 1-8; p. 4 (Box 28, Folder 1388)
    - Manifeste du Futurisme
      - Autograph manuscript draft of the first futurist manifesto, with corrections in pen, pencil and blue crayon. Drawing on page 12. At top of page 1: "La fondation du futurisme et son manifeste". 31 p., numbered 1-[16], 1-17. (Box 57, Folder 2022)
        Restricted material. May not be seen without the permission of the appropriate curator. Copy filed in box 28, folder 1389. Also available at http://brbl-dl.library.yale.edu/vufind/Record/3483113
      - Photocopy of: Autograph manuscript draft of the first futurist manifesto, with corrections in pen, pencil and blue crayon. Drawing on page 12. At top of page 1: "La fondation du futurisme et son manifeste". 31 p., numbered 1-[16], 1-17. (Box 28, Folder 1389)
        See also: Series III, Box 16, folder 974
    - Manifeste technique de la littérature futuriste
      - Printed version, with comments in the margins in hand of FTM. 8 p., numbered 163-170. (Box 28, Folder 1390)
    - Manifesto del Naturismo-futurista
      - Autograph manuscript in an unidentified hand (Arnaldo Ginna?), with additions and corrections in the hand of FTM. Signed on last page by FTM and Arnaldo Ginna. 7 p. (Box 28, Folder 1391)
    - Manifesto futurista del romanzo sintetico
      - Typescript with corrections, possibly in the hand of FTM. Three names at bottom of last page: Filippo Tommaso Marinetti, Luigi Scrivo, and Piero Bellanova. 4 p. (Box 28, Folder 1392)
    - Manifesto Russolo
      - Autograph manuscript, perhaps intended for a speech, with corrections. Several pages cut and pasted together (p. 1-4, 18). The text consists of nine paragraphs from the Manifesto dei pittori futuristi (1910 Feb 11) followed by nine paragraphs from La pittura futurista, manifesto tecnico (1910 Apr 11), by Boccioni, Carra, Russolo, Balla and Severini. On cover and occasionally throughout the manuscript "Russolo" or "R" written in an uniden- tified hand in purple pencil. 27 p., including cover title, numbered 1-25. (Box 28, Folder 1393)
    - Manifesto tecnico della letteratura futurista
      - Autograph manuscript notes for the manifesto and other miscellaneous notes about the avant-garde, Dada, surrealism, Freud, and the meaning of the Futurist movement. 34 p., pages numbered variously Of differing sizes (Box 28, Folder 1394)
        See also: Box 28, folder 1390; Box 35, folder 1614; Box 18, folder 1183; Box 33, folder 1525
    - [Manifesto]
      - Autograph manuscript notes. At top of first page: "Definizione". 5 p., varying sizes (Box 28, Folder 1395)
      - Autograph manuscript notes for "Improvisazione futurista". 2 p., written on telegram paper (Box 28, Folder 1396)
      - Autograph manuscript notes for Manifesto of Tactilism. 5 p. (Box 28, Folder 1397)
        See also: Box 36, folder 1631
      - Autograph manuscript notes for a manifesto about theater. 1 p. (Box 28, Folder 1398)
        See also: Box 37, folder 1640-42
      - Autograph manuscript notes for Feminist Manifesto 9 p., unnumbered (Box 28, Folder 1399)
      - Printed version of manifesto beginning: "Non sempre una generazione sorge in contrasto con la generazione che l'ha preceduta," from unidentified journal, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 1400)
        See also: Box 24, folder 1301; Box 25, folder 1322; Series V, Box 48, folder 1908; Box 37, folder 1640; Box 37, folder 1646; Box 37, folder 1662; Series V, Box 48, folder 1909
    - La Mansarde
      - Two versions of an autograph manuscript poem, both with corrections, signed at bottom of last pages 4 p., each poem 2 pages (Box 28, Folder 1401)
        See also: Box 31, folder 1490
    - Le manuscrit, caricature tragique
      - Autograph manuscript notes for a play, with corrections. 4 p. (Box 28, Folder 1402)
    - Marina piccola
      - Autograph manuscript notes in French and Italian On top of p. 2: "Prelude". 3 p., numbered 1-2. (Box 28, Folder 1403)
    - Marinetti, F.T.
      See: Box 25, folder 1325
    - Marx, Karl
      See: Box 33, folder 1531
    - Massimo Notari
      - Autograph manuscript essay. 84 p., including title- page. Numbered 1-83. (Box 28, Folder 1404)
    - Le matin
      - Autograph manuscript poem. Other notes for poems on verso. 2 p. (Box 28, Folder 1405)
    - Meandri d'un Rio nella foresta brasiliana
      - Typescript, incomplete. 6 p. [Related to: Novelle colle labbra tinte, 1930 (Box 28, Folder 1406)
    - La Méditerranée et son dynamisme
      - Autograph manuscript essay, with corrections. On the versos of pages 1 and 2 drawings of a coastline by FTM. 7 p. (Box 28, Folder 1407)
    - Merli, Gian Franco
      See: Box 33, folder 1541
    - Les métiers
      - A group of various autograph manuscript notes and short essays under this title with several subtitles at the top of different sheets: Suget de piece; Pensées et Maximes... 10 p. (Box 28, Folder 1408)
    - [Milan]
      - Autograph manuscript notes, with corrections. 2 p. (Box 28, Folder 1409)
    - Milazzo, Battaglia di
      - Autograph manuscript outline and notes for an essay, with corrections. 16 p. (Box 28, Folder 1410)
    - [Mimy]
      - Autograph manuscript essay with many corrections, beginning "Tu es fou (?), Mimi? Comment es-tu ici Mimi?..." 8 p. Was originally grouped with Hymne au printemps, Box 26, folder 1349 and Venise Box 38, folders 1370-1372 (Box 28, Folder 1411)
    - Miss Radio
      - Typescript with corrections. 8 p. [Related to: Novelle colle labbra tinte, 1930.] (Box 28, Folder 1412)
    - Misurazione della sensibilità futurista di Bruno Corra e Settimelli
      - Autograph manuscript signed, with corrections. 4 p. (Box 28, Folder 1413)
    - Mon coeur contre la pluie
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections. 7 p., including title-page (Box 28, Folder 1414)
    - [Montecarlo]
      - Autograph manuscript outline, with corrections, of a book on Montecarlo, with a note on the last page "piano di libro Montecarlo". 11 p. (Box 28, Folder 1415)
    - Montecarlo
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections. 2 p. (Box 28, Folder 1416)
    - La mort de la lune
      - Autograph manuscript poem in an unidentified hand, possibly FTM's. 8 p. (Box 28, Folder 1417)
    - Il movimento di aeropittura
      - Autograph manuscript essay with many corrections 6 p. (Box 28, Folder 1418)
    - [Music]
      - Small card with scales drawn on it in ink and pen- cil. "Violino" written at top, in hand of FTM? 1 p. (Box 28, Folder 1419)
    - Musicalità della poesia futurista
      - Autograph manuscript outline including names of poets important to futurism. 5 p. (Box 28, Folder 1420)
    - [Naples]
      - Autograph manuscript notes about Naples. In lower right corner of page 1: "La Zolfatara di Napoli" Page 1 is written on the verso of a TLS to FTM from the Ente Italiano per le Audizioni Radiofoniche signed Lefozzi, 3 May 1930. 2 p. (Box 28, Folder 1421)
    - Navigation tactile
      - Autograph manuscript poem signed at bottom of last page. 10 p. (Box 57, Folder 2023)
        Restricted material. May not be seen without the permission of the appropriate curator. Photocopy filed in box 28, folder 1422.
      - Photocopy of: Autograph manuscript poem signed at bottom of last page. 10 p. (Box 28, Folder 1422)
    - Navigation tactile (Poésie tactile mots en liberté).
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections. Signed on bottom of last page. An earlier version of IV.18.3. 5 p., numbered [1]-5 and also 252-256 in red pencil at top of each page (Box 28, Folder 1423)
    - Navigazione tattile
      - Autograph manuscript poem, apparently in the hand of FTM, signed at bottom of last page. Italian version of IV.18.3-5. 6 p. (Box 28, Folder 1424)
    - [Nietzsche]
      - Autograph manuscript essay on Nietzsche. In French 8 p. (Box 28, Folder 1425)
    - [Notari trial]
      - Autograph manuscript essay, with corrections, signed by FTM on last page. The first paragraph explains that this is an Italian translation of an article by FTM that appeared in the Parisian newspaper Gil Blas concerning the Notari trial. 22 p. (Box 28, Folder 1426)
        See also: Box 26, folder 1362
    - [Notari, Umberto]
      - Typescript essay, with corrections in FTM's hand, about Umberto Notari 5 p. (Box 28, Folder 1427)
    - Notes sur "Salammbô"
      See: Box 27, folder 1384
    - La nouvelle poesie de la machine futuriste...
      - Autograph manuscript outline for an essay, with corrections. 4 p. (Box 28, Folder 1428)
    - La nouvelle religion morale de la vitesse
      - Autograph manuscript notes with corrections. On cover title: "Notes et traduction française du manifeste du Religion morale de la Vitesse" and "Ebauches de poèmes français." 49 p., varying sizes, including cover title (Box 28, Folder 1429)
    - La Nouvelle religion morale de la vitesse, manifeste
      - Autograph manuscript with a few corrections, possibly in the hand of FTM, at bottom of last page signed "M. traduit très mal" 17 p. (Box 28, Folder 1430)
        See also: Box 28, folder 1433
    - [Novel]
      - Autograph manuscript draft of a novel, heavily corrected, with portions of pages pasted on other pages. Some of the headings at the top of the page refer to "Orgo". In Italian. 40 p., numbered incon- sistently (Box 28, Folder 1431)
    - Les nuages firent des signes
      - Autograph manuscript, with corrections. 6 p., 4 p. with 2 p. cover title (Box 28, Folder 1432)
    - La Nueva Religion-Moral de Velocidad
      - Autograph manuscript translation of FTM's manifesto "La nouvelle religion morale de la vitesse", with a few corrections. 20 p., numbered [1]-20. (Box 28, Folder 1433)
        See also: Box 28, folders 1429-30
    - La nuit des indomptables
      - Autograph manuscript, with a few corrections Continued in IV.19.2. Signed on title-page. 150 p., including cover title. Numbered [1]-149. (Box 29, Folder 1434)
      - Autograph manuscript, with a few corrections. Second part of IV.l9.1. 256 p., numbered 150-391. (Box 29, Folder 1435)
      - Typescript carbon, with corrections, additions, and editorial instructions by FTM 223 p., including title-page, numbered [1]-218. Bound in construction paper with tacks (Box 29, Folder 1436)
      - Typescript carbon, more extensively corrected than IV.19.3. 224 p., including title-page, numbered [1]-218. Bound in construction paper with tacks (Box 29, Folder 1437)
    - "Nuove battaglie per l'italianità di tulla l'arte moderna"
      - Printed version, Autori e Scrittori, 1938 Dec (Box 29, Folder 1438)
    - "L'Oceano del Cuore"
      - Excerpt, printed version, Brillante, 1927 Dec 21
    - Offrande à la mer
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with many corrections Title on verso of last page. 4 p., numbered 1-4. (Box 29, Folder 1439)
    - Les ombres traquées
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with many corrections 9 p. (Box 29, Folder 1440)
    - [O'Neill, Eugene]
      - Autograph manuscript notes about Eugene O'Neill, identified as "O Neal futurista americano..." Also includes outline for essay on simultaneity of time and space. 8 p. (Box 29, Folder 1441)
        See also: Box 35, folder 1599
    - Originalità Russa di Masse Distanze Radiocuori
      - Carbon copy of a typescript, with no corrections Accompanied by a small piece of paper, in FTM's hand?, with a correspondence between manuscript and typescript pages. This numberical correspondence is separated each time by one word followed by a question mark. 119 p., numbered 1-118 (2 pages 83s) (Box 29, Folder 1442)
      - A second carbon copy, with no corrections, except for one page which is original typed sheet. 119 p., numbered 1-118, (including two page 83s). (Box 29, Folder 1443)
      - Original typescript, with corrections in FTM's hand, and inserted into the middle of the typescript is a manuscript page in an unidentified hand labeled at the top: "Parole russe da controllare". 120 p., numbered 1-118 (including two of page 83) and an inserted ms. page after p. 70, that lists correspondences of Russian and Italian words (Box 29, Folder 1444)
    - La Pace dei Campi
      - Autograph manuscript essay written on the verso of a letter to FTM from the Regia Universita Italiana per Stranieri of Perugia, dated 29 May 1929. Enclosed in an envelope with a different title and, at the bottom, "Marinetti e Azari". 2 p. (Box 30, Folder 1445)
    - "Il Paesaggio nei sentimenti e nelle poesie di Napoli"
      - Printed version, Roma, 1935 Jun 5
    - La Palma Italia
      - Carbon typescript, with extended title at top of page 1: "Le eleganze della palma italia, ricca dei suoi datteri paradisiaci. Aeropoema futurista con parole in libertà olfattive Tattili da rappresentare teatralmente in una Oasi". 122 p., including title- page, numbered [1]-122 (p. 104-5 on one page). (Box 30, Folder 1446)
      - Carbon typescript, same as IV.21.1. 122 p., inclu- ding title-page, numbered [1]-122. In green manila folder, with title written on cover (in hand of BCM). (Box 30, Folder 1447)
      - Carbon typescript, same as IV.21.1. 122 p., inclu- ding title-page, numbered [1]-122. In green manila folder, with title and FTM's name written on cover by BCM (Box 30, Folder 1448)
    - [Pan Club] [i.e. P.E.N. Club]
      - Autograph manuscript note about Pan Club, Budapest and Buenos Aires. On top of page: "Risposta". 1 p. (Box 30, Folder 1449)
    - Paolo Baglione
      See: Box 31, folder 1470 and Box 23, folders 1283-84
    - Le parfum de ta chair
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections. 1 p. (Box 30, Folder 1450)
    - [Parole in libertà]
      - Autograph manuscript notes beginning: "Parole in libertà." 1 p. (Box 30, Folder 1451)
        See also: Box 36, folder 1631 and Box 37, folder 1643
    - [Passo Uarieu]
      - Autograph manuscript notes, with many corrections and a diagram, relating to Passo Uarieu. 2 p. (Box 30, Folder 1452)
        See also: Box 32, folder 1497
    - [Patriottismo insetticida, Romanzo di avventure legislative]
      - Typescript with corrections in the hand of FTM. The title-page is labelled: "Alla Ricerca di una nuova morale, Romanzo d'avventure legislative", and above it in the hand of FTM: "Bozze e scorie(?) di patriottismo insetticida." 141 p., including title-page. Numbered 1-140. Index on p. 140. (Box 30, Folder 1453)
      - Carbon typescript of IV.21.7, with corrections in FTM's hand. Missing chapter 7 ("Il poema dei Languori del Golfo di Napoli", p. 74-81). 133 p., missing 74-81. (Box 30, Folder 1454)
    - [Patriottismo insetticida]
      - Autograph manuscript notes on Patriottismo insetticida and other issues. 22 p., varying sizes (Box 30, Folder 1455)
        See also: Box 21, folder 1248
      - Autograph manuscript notes with heading at the top; "Alla ricerca di una nuova morale". 1 p. (Box 30, Folder 1456)
      - Typescript fragments, both original and carbon 26 p. (Box 30, Folder 1457)
      - Proof with extensive corrections by FTM. At the end, eight manuscript pages, possibly in the hand of FTM 174 p., numbered inconsistently (Box 30, Folder 1458)
      - Uncorrected proof, still retaining the earlier title of "Alla Ricerca di una nuova morale". 160 p., num- bered [1]-[197] (Box 30, Folder 1459)
      - Proof with correct title, no corrections in the text. 161 p., numbered [1]-[194] (Box 31, Folder 1460)
    - Paysage d'odeurs de mon chien-loup, (poésie olfactive mots en liberté).
      - Autograph manuscript (fragment of a larger work) with a few corrections, signed on the last page 7 p., numbered [1]-7 in pen and 268-274 in red pencil (Box 31, Folder 1461)
    - Paysage d'odeurs de mon chien-loup.
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with title written twice on the verso of the last page. 21 p., numbered 1-21. (Box 31, Folder 1462)
    - P.E.N. Club
      See: Box 30, folder 1449
    - Pensées de nuit tombante (prière à la tristesse).
      - Autograph manuscript essay with corrections, signed at the end of page 3 and dated 27 May 1898. Title on last page: "Prière à la tristesse." 5 p. (Box 31, Folder 1463)
    - Piccola macchina lirica
      - Autograph manuscript poem with title at top of page 1, in pencil. 5 p., numbered [1]-5. (Box 57, Folder 2024)
        Restricted material. May not be seen without the permission of the appropriate curator. Photocopy filed in box 31, folder 1464.
      - Photocopy of: Autograph manuscript poem with title at top of page 1, in pencil. 5 p., numbered [1]-5. (Box 31, Folder 1464)
    - Piccolo ritratto futurista di Anna Fougez
      - Autograph manuscript essay. 2 p. (Box 31, Folder 1465)
    - Piedigrotta futuriste
      - Autograph manuscript, with title on verso of last page followed by: "mots en liberté de Marinetti e Cangiullo, Abstraction dramatique de Balla, Brui- teurs de Russolo." Text in Italian. 8 p., numbered [1]-7. (Box 31, Folder 1466)
    - Pirandello
      - Autograph manuscript outline for an essay on Pirandello. In Italian. 8 p., numbered a-h (Box 31, Folder 1467)
    - [Play]
      - Autograph manuscript notes and outline for a play 4 p. (Box 31, Folder 1468)
    - [Play]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for two plays, "Gli sfocati" (commedia), and "Le mani". 2 p. (Box 31, Folder 1469)
    - [Play]
      - Autograph manuscript play lacking a title-page. In a turquoise folder labeled with FTM's name and the title "Paolo Baglione" in the hand of either FTM or BCM. In French. "Paolo Baglione" was later produced as "Dramma senza titolo." 191 p., numbered 1-68; 1-54; 1-12; 14-26; 1-44 (Box 31, Folder 1470)
        See also: Box 23, folders 1283-84
    - [Poem] A toute vitesse
      See: Box 31, folders 1478
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for a poem. On verso of page 2: "Bois en silence. Bois!" 2 p. (Box 31, Folder 1471)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections, begin- ning: "Comme il partait pour un voyage..." 5 p. (Box 31, Folder 1472)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections, begin- ning "Dopo avere poppato 6 ore..." 4 p., numbered [1]-4. (Box 31, Folder 1473)
        See also: Box 31, folder 1478
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections, begin- ning: "Grazie...per i...". A note written to FTM in another hand on verso of p. 34 in blue pencil. 59 p., numbered 1-65, missing p. 26, 30, 43, 60-62. (Box 31, Folder 1474)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript poem, incomplete, with corrections, beginning: "Immenses filets..." 1 p. (Box 31, Folder 1475)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections, signed at the end. Poem begins: "J'ai fait ce rêve..." 2 p. (Box 31, Folder 1476)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript poem signed and dated at bottom of sheet, Milan, 5 Decembre 1896. Begins: "Je veux pour toi l'amour..." 1 p. (Box 31, Folder 1477)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for various poems, in- cluding La Lutte and a list of other poems on page 1. Also in this group is a draft of "Un Soir... de Paroles" (Le Demon de la Vitesse) and "A toute Vitesse (Les trains)". 15 p. (Box 31, Folder 1478)
        See also: Box 37, folder 1653
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript poem with corrections, begin- ning: "Mon bel ange sensuel, brûlant et trempé..." 3 p., numbered [1]-3. (Box 31, Folder 1479)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections, begin- ning: "Nous étions étrangers..." Signed and dated after last line 1 Settembre 1896. With additional notes in pencil at the bottom of page 2. 2 p. (Box 31, Folder 1480)
    - [Poem, Parole in Libertà]
      - Autograph manuscript poem with drawings, beginning: "tutto tutto tutto tutto per la patria..." 5 p. (Box 31, Folder 1481)
        See also: Box 31, folder 1472
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript poem with corrections begin- ning: "Un soir qu'il ferait noir..." 2 p. (Box 31, Folder 1482)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript poem, [1943], beginning "volto, volto, volto..." 1 p. (Box 31, Folder 1483)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript fragment of a poem beginning on p. 3: "Ne lance pas trop loin ton coeur..." 5 p. (Box 31, Folder 1484)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for a poem beginning "Buc, bianco..." 16 p., pages of varying sizes (Box 31, Folder 1485)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript notes, possibly for various poems, in French. On verso of last page: "Le papere sono rivelazioni del subcosciente direbbe Freud." 19 p. (Box 31, Folder 1486)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for poems about Africa, Marakesh. In Italian. 5 p. (Box 31, Folder 1487)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for a poem beginning "Quando la spiaggia..." 1 p. (Box 31, Folder 1488)
    - [Poem]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for various poems (?) beginning: "Roman..." 11 p. (Box 31, Folder 1489)
    - [Poems]
      - Autograph manuscript poems from 1896 and a few from 1897, mostly in French. In addition to poems, many notes for poetry and other things such as a five- page vocabulary list and two pages of notes on Schopenhauer, Whitman, Wyzewa and others and four pages of notes on Maurice Barrès. 188 p. Among the identified poems are: (Box 31, Folder 1490)
        Notte lunare, 2 p. Baisers, 4 p. with notes Erotica, 2 p. with notes La jeunesse est radieuse, 1 p., 1897 Jan 26 Un rêve, 2 p. Rêves, impressions, silhouettes, 4 p.
        Rupture, 1 p. 1896 Jan[?] 2 Rupture d'amour, 5 p. with notes Le réveil du Dieu Soleil, 1 p. 1896 Jul 25 A Mademoiselle M..., 1 p. with notes Adieu, crépusculaire, 7 p. Crepuscolo marino, 2 p. Fatalité d'amour, 2 p. Crepuscolo, 2 p.
        Couchant d'automne, 1 p. Macabres luxures, 1 p. 1896 Jul 29 [?] Amours funèbres, 4 p. 1896 Aug 22 Les nuages, 14 p. 1896 Aug 12 Vos sourires, 1 p. with 7 pp. of drafts of letters in the hand of FTM to unidentified recipient Le tremplin de mes rêves, 8 p. with 3 pp. noted for a poem "Le Parfum de ta Peau" Chateaubriand, 1 p. Paysages abolis, 4 p.
        Conseils du soir, 1 p. 1896 Dec 16 Diptyque de la lune, 2 p. Légende andalouse, 6 p. with notes La filandière, 3 p. with notes Pour la porte des Courtisanes [and] Pour la porte des Prêtresses, 2 p. Sonnet à ma plume, 1 p.
        Vers l'ideal, 1 p. Aube, 2 p. Ballade, 1 p. l'échanson des nuits, 4 p. 1897 Jan 16 Amour!, 1 p. 1896 Jun 14[?] Le Soir et la Ville, 2 p.
        Le douce prison, 5 p. with notes "J'éprouve a t'aimer...", 2 p. "Odeur des bêtes féroces...", 2 p. II. Sonnet, 1 p. La Maisonnette, 2 p. 1896 Dec 3 Vers le soir, 2 p. Couchant, 1 p.
        "Aux premières heures du monde...", 3 p., numbered 2-4 "Car le soir est venu...", 4 p. L'amour boudeur[?] (beginning: "Nous etions étrangers l'un a l'autre..."), 8 p. 1896 Sep 1 Votre jeu[?], 1 p. "Dédicace A Mademoiselle Louise Galtinoire[?]", 1 p. Au delà de la mort, 1 p.
        "IIeme Partie de la 'Une suggestion Criminelle'", 2 p. Cher Calamus, 1 p. "Vous êtes...", 1 p. "Couchant en fusion...", 4 p. with "Le jeune prince..." on verso of last page "Et je te vois debut...", 1 p.
        12 fragments of poems
    - Poem
      See: Box 24, folder 1308, group O and group P
    - [Poema africano]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for the Poema africano, with many corrections. 30 p., unnumbered, varying sizes (Box 32, Folder 1491)
    - Poema africano